In this video, we will be looking at
graphical
kinematics and how position relates with
velocity
and how that relates with acceleration.
Basically, in graphical kinematics, before
AP
Physics C, or in normal high school
physics,
you will not need to use calculus to use
this.
So the questions are going to be
relatively
easy. The main thing that you need to know
is
that velocity is the slope of the
position.
And acceleration is the slope of the
velocity.
So if you think of position as y, and if
you
know calculus, velocity would just be y
prime
and acceleration would be y double prime.
Or acceleration would be the slope of the
position
and velocity would just be the slope of
the
position. If that sounds hard to you and
you
don't know calculus, let me make this
easier
for you. Let's say the position was going
like
this. If the position is in the shape of a
parabola,
then the velocity is going to be the slope
at
every point. And the velocity would look
something
like this. It would just increase in a
straight
line. And since the velocity is increasing
in
a straight line, the acceleration would be
the
same everywhere because the slope of this
line
is just one. So basically, if this
position
was y equals x squared, then the equation
of the velocity line graph would be equal
to
y equals x and acceleration would be y
equals
one. Or in this case, y is a, velocity is
v, and position is p.
And x in this case is always t because
this
is a position over time. The x-axis in
these
types of graphs is always t.
So let's try another example.
Let's say the position this time is
increasing
at a steady rate. And we need to draw the
graphs
for velocity and acceleration.
Well, let's see. We need to find the slope
of
this position first of all. This is time
and
this is the respective value. So what is
the
slope of this? Well, looking at it, slope
is
change in y over change in x.
So delta-y, delta-x.
So the slope is two. So since the slope is
two
at any point in this graph, that means
that the velocity will be constant because
the
slope is the same at any point in the
graph.
So since the slope is two, the velocity
will
be two at every single point. Now the
acceleration
is the slope of the velocity. Now if the
velocity
is just a horizontal line, because this
has
the same slope, then the slope of a
horizontal
line is always zero. So there will not be
an
acceleration here. And when you think
about
it, it makes sense. When the position is
steadily
increasing at a constant rate, that means
the
velocity or the speed of that object is
going
to be the same and it's not going to be
undergoing
any acceleration. Let's see another
example.
This time we need to derive the position
from
an acceleration. Let's say we have an
acceleration
one. Usually acceleration doesn't go up
and
down. It's an instantaneous change.
So over here, and then we will experience
zero
acceleration. Now we have to work
backwards.
As we can see, from time zero to two, the
acceleration
is one metres per second squared.
So that means the slope from time zero to
two
will be equal to one. So it's going to be
linear
with a slope of one. Next, from time two
to
four, the slope is going to be three. So
we're
going to go over a bit, but let's say this
is
eight. It's going to go all the way up to
eight
in a straight line. Because since the
acceleration
is constant, the velocity is increasing at
a
constant rate of a slope of three.
So this is a slope of three. And now,
finally,
the acceleration goes down to zero, which
means
that the velocity is going to have a slope
of
zero here. Now we can map out the
position.
The position is basically like a parabola
of
what we have. So it's going to look
something
like this, and then it's going to go all
the
way up. So let's just pretend that this is
a
really large number, like 1000.
It's going to look something like that
going
up, and then it's going to constantly
increase
over here. I kind of overshot the
question,
but that's basically the gist of it.
Let me give you another question that is
like
this, but I won't overshoot it this time.
So
we're going to start off with constant
velocity,
and keep in mind that these velocity time
graphs
can go into the negatives as well. So
let's
say if acceleration went down to negative
two,
and then it went up to positive two for
one
second, and then it went up here, and then
it went down to zero. So how would we
depict
the velocity time graph? Try yourself,
pause
the video, and come back when you're
ready.
So first of all, since we start with an
acceleration
of one, we start with a slope of one.
So it's going to go like this, up to time
equals
one. I'm going to label the time here.
And now, from time one to three seconds,
we're
going to be going at a slope of negative
two.
So it's going to have a slope of two.
So it's going to go all the way down to
negative
three. And then we're going to have a
slope
of positive two for one second. So it's
going
to go up here, and then it's going to have
a
slope of one, and then it's going to have
slope of zero. So basically, the key is to
map
out and treat this as a slope.
You treat this as a slope and you map it
out
over here. Now, same thing for position.
We're going to have a parabola looking
sort
of like that. And then we're going to have
a
parabola looking like this, the other way
now,
all the way down to negative nine.
Kind of overshotted again, but it's fine.
And then we're going to have a parabola
that
looks like this, and then a less
steep parabola that goes here.
And then goes over here.
Goes all the way up, back up, and then
flat
down. So that's basically how you do
position,
velocity, and acceleration graphs. You
have
to find the slope of the previous one.
Thank you for watching, and I hope you
found
this helpful. Bye!